Gautam Chandra N

A Motivated Tech Entrepreneur & Web Developer Experience: 7 years, Education: B.Tech. IIIT-Hyderabad Email: gautam4you@gmail.com, Website: http://www.theox.in/ Linkedin | Github | Twitter | Facebook

Summary

Co-Founded and Headed the Engineering of a technology start-up (Moontara).

Experienced in technologies varying from Web Development, Infrastructure Automation to Embedded Programming and Voip Networking.

Experienced in managing and working with remote (US, South Korea, Malaysia, Russia, Ukraine) team members.

Delved in cross-functional roles viz. Team building & management, Quick prototyping with unfamiliar technologies, scoping the product for business with multiple stakeholders.

Most of my experience had been in closed corporates. Recently, started contributing to OSS world.

Technical Skills

Programming Languages: Ruby (Proficient), JavaScript (Proficient), C, PHP

Web Framework: Rails (Proficient), YII

Databases: MySQL

Caching: Memcached, Redis (Limited Exp)

Full text search: Sphinx (Limited Exp), Solr (Limited Exp)

Background Jobs: DelayedJob , SideKiq

Communication Services: Mailgun, Twilio

Infrastructure Automation: Chef

Amazon Web Services: EC2, S3, RDS | (Limited Exp): CloudFront , API Gateway, Lambda, Glacier

Monitoring & Alerting: Airbrake, Pingdom, PagerDuty, Newrelic, Monit

Deployment: Capistrano

Security: Ossec, Clamav, Google Authenticator, IBM Rational Purify

Continuous Integration: Solano Labs

Version Control Systems: Git, Mercurial

Operating Systems: Ubuntu, Windows, Nucleus(*Limited Exp*), centOS (*Limited Exp*)

Others: jQuery

Experience in: Web Applications, Network Programming, Concurrent Programming, Embedded Applications

Managerial Experience

- Owned multiple product lines and managed their releases @Moontara.
- Gathered requirements from customers, sales & operation teams and prioritized releases @Moontara
- Looked into day-to-day operations of the company (15+ employees) @Moontara
- Experience of Agile practices in product development @Moontara, @Chronus
- Lead a team of highly qualified engineers to deliver Campaign Management feature @ Chronus.
- Lead the team of operations for two quarters @ Chronus

Work Experience

Tagalys

Senior Ruby on Rails Consultant

July 2015 - Oct 2015

Tagalys is a *search as a service* provider aiming to provide better search and recommendations to e-commerce sites. They also act as technology consultants for few of their e-commerce clients. *Experience Summary:*

- Built an easily scalable distributed scraper which collect products' information from various Indian e-commerce sites.
- Built an analytics collection library which mines data about the user behaviour & the impressions of products in various widgets of the e-commerce sites.
- Re-vamped one of their clients' website (http://www.vucato.com/) to be mobile friendly.

Chronus Corporation

Feature Team Lead (3 quarters), Operations Team Lead (2 quarters), Senior Software Design Engineer

Aug 2013 - Jun 2015

Chronus is a mentoring and talent development solution provider aimed at easing out processes involved in Career Development programs. The solutions are majorly built on Ruby on Rails stack.

Experience Summary:

- Owned & delivered *Campaign Management* a generic behavioural driven drip-campaign feature. It was used to increase signup rates and profile completion scores.
- As Operations team lead: Introduced several disaster recovery policies as part of Business
 Continuity measures, Introduced several tools which eased out operational effort and secured
 production servers viz., Google-Authenticator, SSH Gateway, Twilio etc..
- As a lead, organized daily scrums, conducted RCAs and Sprint Retros which helped in smooth rollout and maintenance of features.

Skills:

Team management, Infrastructure Automation and Monitoring, Agile Software Development, Release Management, Scoping Deliverables, Customer Service Team Interaction, System Security, Streamlining internal operations and processes.

Technologies:

Ruby on Rails, Ruby, Chef, Javascript, JQuery, MySQL

Globalization of Questions Framework (Lead) & Support for Campaign Management (Lead):

Feb 2015 – May 2015

- As part of globalizing the entire product, led a sub-team which focused on globalizing question
 related use-cases of the product. As profile questions were tangled with various use-cases of the
 product, analysed the impact of the problem and proposed a short-cut but maintainable
 approach which reduced the cost of development to 30% of the original estimate.
- Headed the maintenance of Campaign Management feature and guided team members in delivering minor feature requests and issue fixes.

Technologies Used: Globalize3 gem, I18n

Campaign Management (Feature Team Lead):

- Designed and led the development of Campaign Management a generic behavioural driven drip-campaign eco-system, USPs of which include personalization & analytics of emails.
- Designed the architecture to be generic and integrated with two important business use-cases (user campaigns & driving signup) of the Chronus product.
- Optimized email delivery times by exploring and setting up Mailgun batch sends.

May 2014 – Jan 2015 • As the feature lead, took care of daily routines like scrums, sprintly routines like RCA & Retros, monthly routines like OKR check-ins and quarterly routines like 1-1 Reviews.

Technologies Used: Ruby, Ruby on Rails, Mailgun, Delayed Jobs

Lead of Operations Nov 2013 – Apr 2014

- Explored and introduced Google-Authenticator for two-way SSH authentication to production servers.
- Created two pools of servers, one for production environments and the other one for staging environments. SSH access to the production servers was made possible only through a SSH Gateway machine.
- Explored and setup an automated way (Twilio) to send sensitive information as SMS to Chronus Mentor Customer Success Team.
- Scripted various disaster recovery policies using aws-sdk and Chef.
- Made the Chronus Mentor product HTTPS compatible.

Technologies Used: AWS, Chef, aws-sdk, Twilio, Google-Authenticator

Moontara Technovations Co-Founder & Chief Engineer

Sep 2010 – Jun 2013 Exposure: Across Indian cities

Summary:

- Led the development of various Moontara Products (myTV, C2V, SMS Wall, Virtual Showroom, and HDTV Video Wall).
- Followed agile practices in software development and release management.
- Explored and finalized hardware required for Moontara Products.
- Designed Alerts framework a pro-active approach in customer service.
- Designed the architecture of myTV (Moontara's flagship Digital Signage Application) as a platform for display apps.
- Database Design and Administration of Moontara products.
- Built prototypes to test the feasibility of business ideas.
- Built the development team from scratch.

Skills: Team building & management, Agile Software Development, Release Management, Structuring development processes, Product road-mapping, Quick Prototyping, Streamlining operations

Moontara Products Info:

myTV:

Jan 2011 – Present

- myTV is the Moontara's Flagship digital signage Application.
- It can be used to control what to show where and when on ones' digital displays. One can even schedule live TV broadcast (through STB) along with the advertisements.
- The control is given from Moontara's Web portal hosted on Amazon EC2 cloud.
- The product exposes RESTful api for easy app development.

Technologies Used: C,C++, php, nodejs, jQuery, Directshow, DirectX, YII

C2V (Click-to-View): Oct 2011 - Present

- This innovative product enables instant photo sharing on digital displays powered by Moontara's mvTV.
- The photos can be taken from any digital camera that support SD card and are uploaded through wifi in less than 40 seconds after clicking!
- It can even push photos to social networking platforms like Facebook & Twitter.

Technologies Used: python, nodejs, nodewebkit, myTV REST api

HDTV Video Wall: Jul 2012 – Present

• This product enables electronic retail outlets to show advertisements on their for-sale HDTVs.

- It enabled Croma's Internal Marketing team to sell 1700 HDTVs as a space on hire for advertisers.
- Deployed the solution in Croma's 22 biggest stores of Bangalore, Mumbai and Delhi.
- Cloud based monitoring drastically reduced the operational cost.
- Successfully fixed all the technology and operational issues faced while integrating with store's
 existing setups.

Technologies Used: myTV with HDMI out

Virtual Showroom: Jul 2012 - Present

• It is a "Virtual Showroom" application developed on a kiosk that helps customer access the complete range of products of an automobile manufacturer in an interactive way.

Technologies Used: jQuery, javascript

SMS Wall: Feb 2012 – Mar

 Used in one of the BNI conferences, SMS Wall provides an effective medium for the members to broadcast their messages.

• The messages sent through SMS are pushed onto a 200inch projector screen powered by myTV.

Technologies Used: Snowwebs SMS Gateway, myTV REST api

Scrapped Projects

Wifi STB: Sep 2010 – Dec 2010

• This product enables multiple channel viewing using a single STB (Set-top-box). It takes advantage of the unused tuner, Ethernet port of a typical STB.

In-store TV @ IT Hubs: Apr 2012 – Jan 2013

• This *myTV* powered product provided a medium for electronic brands to advertise in IT-Hubs like S.P.Road (Bangalore) and Lamington Road (Mumbai).

Samsung India Software Operations Senior Software Engineer

Jul 2008 – Sep 2010 Exposure: Russia, South Korea, Malaysia

2012

Summary:

- Media buffer management for IMS based VOIP and VT calls over Wimax networks.
- Abstracting sockets layer of Nucleus OS for easy integration with various multimedia protocols.
- Design and Implementation of Adaptive Jitter Buffer for VOIP calls. Fine-tuning it onsite for network providers like YOTA (Russia) and YTL (Malaysia).
- Ported TLS1.0 for secure SIP based Presence for wimax handsets

Skills: Socket Programming, Concurrent Programming, Global Interaction and Demonstration, New Technology (WiMAX) adoption, Research of available techniques

Wimax based Mobile for YTL:

YTL: The biggest WiMAX mobile operator as of 2010

• Ported TLS1.0 for secure SIP based Presence for wimax handsets.

- Part of the IMS' media team responsible for VOIP calls.
- Overlooked the media buffer management and data services layer of the WiMAX handsets
- Achieved considerable increase in VOIP quality with simple AJB tweaks, shared the knowledge with other media teams of Samsung IMS.

Feb 2010 – Sep 2010 Exposure: South

Korea, Malaysia

Wimax based Mobile for YOTA:
World's first dual chipset (Wimax + GSM) phone

Sep 2009 - Jan 2010

Part of the IMS' media team responsible for VOIP calls.

- Overlooked the media buffer management and data services layer of the WiMAX handsets
- Onsite fine tuning of the adaptive jitter buffer to meet the requirements of the operator.

Member of IMS media team

Sep 2008 - Aug 2009

Exposure: Russia

- Part of the team responsible for media buffer redesign for VOIP calls over WiMAX.
- Was given ownership to increase the quality of VOIP calls as reported by VQT tools.
- Initiated the idea of Adaptive Jitter Buffer instead of existing Static Jitter Buffer after going through multiple research papers.
- Designed AJB, got it approved from media experts and implemented it for IMS team.
- Involved in the re-architecture of socket abstraction layer for WiMAX handsets.

Mini-Project

Jul 2008 - Sep 2008

• Enabled persistent connection support on the existing HTTP stack.

Personal Initiatives

- Exfm favourite music downloader [python]
- Virtual Keyboard Logger [C, win32 API]
- MITM using ARP spoof [C, winpcap, raw sockets]
- Automated ticket raiser in Trello [nodejs]

Honours & Awards

- NASSCOM Innovation Award 2011 Moontara rated among the Top 7 innovative start-ups in India.
- **Samsung Star Award** Recognition for design and development of Adaptive Jitter Buffer for VOIP calls over Wimax networks, which increased the scores of VQT tool.

Education

B.Tech. ECE, IIIT-Hyderabad

Jul 2004 - Jul 2008

Achievements

- Secured an All India Rank of 716 in AIEEE-2004
- Secured 146th rank in EAMCET-2004
- Scored 96.8% in intermediate board examination of Andhra Pradesh